Guide to the American Indian Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
American Indian collection
1647-1940
MS 35
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
(2 boxes, 1 folio)
An artificial collection of correspondence, writings, photographs, and miscellanea relating to American Indians, including the Mohegan Indians of Connecticut, 1740-1750. Other items include an Iroquois language dictionary and essays such as "Geronimo and His Band in Exile," by Marion E. Stephens, "The Indian River Village Site, Milford, Connecticut," and a narrative on Joseph Morgan Wilcox.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
The entire collection is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 59 instead of the originals.
Existence and Location of Copies
Entire collection is also available on microfilm (HM 59) (648 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Scholarly Resources, Inc., Wilmington, Delaware.
Scope and Contents
An artificial collection of correspondence, writings, photographs, and miscellanea relating to American Indians, including the Mohegan Indians of Connecticut, 1740-1750. Other items include an Iroquois language dictionary and essays such as "Geronimo and His Band in Exile," by Marion E. Stephens, "The Indian River Village Site, Milford, Connecticut," and a narrative on Joseph Morgan Wilcox.
Indians of North America -- Connecticut; Indians of North America; Indians, Treatment of -- North America; Iroquois Indians; Mohegan Indians; Geronimo, 1829-1909; Stephens, Marion E.; Willcox, Joseph Morgan, 1790-1814
- Inventory
  Scope and Contents
  Note: Items that were in box 2 folders 3, 4, and 11,marked with an asterisk (*), are oversized and have been placed in a folio, box 3. This material is available on Hist. MSS Film No. 59.
  - Legal documents concerning Indians in Connecticut, 1647-1795 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
  - Treaty with Five Nations, 1704 October 18 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
  - Schuyler, Peter: ALS to an unknown person concerning a French-Indian attack on New England, 1707 (Box 1, Folder 3, Reel 1U)
  - Copy of a letter to Major Israel Hewitt from Isaac Huntington concerning the trespassing of Indians on his property, 1750 May 14 (Box 1, Folder 4, Reel 1U)
  - Lincoln Benjamin: "Observations on the Indians of North America; containing an answer to some remarks of Doctor Ramsay published in the collections of the Massachusetts Historical Society for 1795" (manuscript) (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - Iroquois language dictionary, Circa 18—? (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - "A Narrative of the Life and Death of Lieutenant Joseph Morgan Wilcox" (manuscript), 1816 (Box 1, Folder 7, Reel 1U)
  - "Records of Convention at Cattaraugus", 1836 January (Box 1, Folder 8, Reel 1U)
  - Documents concerning Indian lands and other Indian problems in New York (state), including three bills and a report of the New York Legislature and two speeches and a report by Peter Wilson, an Indian chief., 1848-1850 (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
  - Jane Lowery: journal, 1756 (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
  - Marion E. Stephens: "Geronimo and His Band in Exile," (typescript, with photographs, drawings, and negatives laid in), undated (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
  - Photograph of unidentified group of four Indians, undated (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
  - Edward H. Rogers: "The Indian River Village Site, Milford, Connecticut", 1940 (Box 1, Folder 13, Reel 1U)
  - The Mohegan Indian Case
    - To the right honble the lords of the committee of his majestys most honble privy council...to prepare the draft of a commission of reviews to certain persons to hear...the Mohegan Indians who complain of grievances received from the people of Connecticut... Whitehall, August 8, 1740. (Box 2, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
    - Between old John Uncas and the greater part of the tribe of the Mohegan Indians by their guardians, appellants [and] the governor and company of his majesty's English colony of Connecticut in New England in America and George Richards Esqr and others, respondents... [after 1742?] (Box 2, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
    - [Petition of appeal for the respondts: the gov.r & Co.] (*) (Box 3, Reel 1U)
    - The Mohegan's position or claim to the Commrs. (*) (Box 3, Reel 1U)
    - The Colonys defence [after 1742?] (Box 2, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
    - The humble address and declaration of Ben Uncas chief sachem of the Mohegan Indians to his majesty's Court of Commissr holden att Norwich in his majesty's English colony of Connecticut in New England... 20 July 1743. (Box 2, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
    - Letter signed "Dr. Sr." discussing the case between Connecticut & the Mohegan Indians. (Box 2, Folder 7, Reel 1U)
    - [Decision of King's court of commissioners in the dispute between Connecticut and the Mohegan Indians] 16 August 1743. (Box 2, Folder 8, Reel 1U)
    - Index to papers relating to the Mohegan Indian Case 1661-1743. (Box 2, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
    - To the honourable the Court of Commission appointed to rexamine, review, finally decide and determine a certain cause or controversy depending between the govr and company of the colony of Connecticut and the Mohegan Indians... Signed: William Bollen (Bollan?) (Box 2, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
    - To George the 2nd King of Great Britain etc. in council the petition of Richd Partridge agent for the colony of Connect in America... London, Dec 26, 1750. (*) (Box 3, Reel 1U)